Guide to the Compressed Air and Free Air Shaft, Tunnel, Foundation, Caisson, Subway, Cofferdam, Sewer Construction Workers, of New York and New Jersey States and Vicinity Records WAG.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Compressed Air and Free Air, Shaft, Tunnel, Foundation, Caisson, Subway, Cofferdam, Sewer Construction Workers, of New York and New Jersey States and Vicinity Records
1938-1975; 2008
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Compressed Air and Free Air, Shaft, Tunnel, Foundation, Caisson, Subway, Cofferdam, Sewer Construction Workers of New York & New Jersey States & Vicinity
WAG.002
1 Linear Feet (1 box)
The Compressed Air and Foundation Workers' Union was chartered by the American Federation of Labor in 1904 and merged with the International Hod Carriers', Building and Common Laborers' Union of America in 1918. Local 147, representing New York metropolitan area "sandhogs" was formed through the merger of Locals 45 and 102 in 1938. The records consist of photocopies of minutes, agreements, constitutions, work rules, and some newspaper clippings.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Compressed Air and Free Air, Shaft, Tunnel, Foundation, Caisson, Subway, Cofferdam, Sewer Construction Workers, of New York and New Jersey States and Vicinity in 1978. The accession number associated with this gift is 1978.011.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Compressed Air and Foundation Workers' Union was chartered by the American Federation of Labor in 1904 and merged with the International Hod Carriers', Building and Common Laborers' Union of America in 1918. Local 147, representing New York metropolitan area "sandhogs" was formed from the merger of Locals 45 and 102 in 1938. Local 102 itself was formed through the merger of Locals 63, 67 (northern New Jersey), and 68 (Newark, NJ). Members have been employed in all major sewage, water, subway and traffic tunnel construction in the New York/New Jersey metropolitan area. Originally composed almost exclusively of Irish and English skilled workers, the union has gradually been opened to minority workers since World War II. In 1978 the union formed a Political Action Committee, funded by a voluntary check-off of three cents per hour, and his since engaged in vigorous political lobbying on issues of concern to members, including health and safety. According to Paul E. Delaney's Sandhogs: A History of the Tunnel Workers of New York (New York: Longfield Press, 1983), which includes several interviews with local members, Local 147 has a well-deserved reputation for democratic practice and member participation.
Scope and Content Note
The records consist for the most part of photocopies of Regular (i.e., membership) Meeting and Executive Board minutes, agreements and newspaper clippings. (Original materials were loaned to the Wagner Labor Archives by Local 147.) The minutes reflect collective bargaining, work rules, and the changing ethnic composition of tunnel work. Also included are original printed copies of a constitution, an agreement, Working Rules booklets and a CD copy of a 2005 television program about the "sandhogs."
Arrangement
Series I is arranged chronologically; series II is arranged alphabetically by topic.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
I, Correspondence, 1938-1960
II, Subject Files, 1949-1975; 2008.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Sandhogs |x History |z New York (State) |z New York .; Minutes (administrative records); Agreements.; Clippings (information artifacts); Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Constitutions.; Underwater construction |x History.; Tunneling |x History.; Underground construction |x History.; Collective bargaining -- New York (State) -- New York.; Compressed Air and Free Air, Shaft, Tunnel, Foundation, Caisson, Subway, Cofferdam, Sewer Construction Workers of New York & New Jersey States & Vicinity
- Series I: Minutes, 1938-1960.
  - Regular Meeting Minutes, Mar 1938-Mar 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Regular Meeting Minutes, Apr 1939-Jun 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Regular Meeting Minutes, Jul 1940-Jul 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Regular Meeting Minutes, Mar 1949-Dec 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Regular Meeting Minutes, Jan 1950-Dec 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Regular Meeting Minutes, Jan 1953-Nov 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Regular Meeting Minutes, Jan 1956-Oct 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Regular Meeting Minutes, Nov 1958-Jul 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Executive Board Minutes, Jul 1941-Jul 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Executive Board Minutes, Aug 1949-Oct 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Executive Board Minutes, Nov 1950-Dec 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Executive Board Minutes, Jan 1953-Nov 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Executive Board Minutes, Feb 1956-Jan 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Executive Board Minutes, Feb 1958-Jul 1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1949-1975; 2008.
  - Agreements, 1949-1957 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Agreements (unsigned), 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Agreements, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Agreements, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Constitution and By-laws (printed, original), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Sandhogs: The Greatest Tunnel Ever Built": Dir. Eddie Rosenstein (Broadcast, 11/5/2008; CD copy) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Working Rules (printed, original), Undated, 1952, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)